罗德尼  你可以说了
You can go ahead, rodney.
我不知道该从哪讲起好
I don't remember where to start.
你能行的
Sure you do.
不
No.
从自报姓名说起吧
Start with your name
就像我们以前做过那样
Like we've been doing, okay,
我们现在就从你名字开始
And we'll just go from there.
我的名字
My name...
我是
My name is...
罗德尼·麦凯先生
Mr. rodney mckay.
说错了
No...
没有
Yes.
加油  再想想
Come on, now.
你是麦凯博士  记得吗
You're dr. mckay, remember?
不  我不是博士了
No, I'm-- I'm not anymore.
我再也不聪明了
I'm not s-s-smart anymore.
博士是很聪明的  我现在只能是先生了
Doctors are smart, so I'm mister now.
好吧
Okay.
我以前是最聪明的人
I used to be the smartest person ever...
而  现在  我不是了
And-- and now... now I'm not.
所以我们现在正努力治好你
That's what we're trying to fix, right?
不  不  你们治不好我的
No. no, you can't fix me.
你知道我们正全力想办法
You know we're trying our very best--
不  你们治不好的
No, you can't.
治不好的  治不好的
You can't. can't--
罗德尼  好好  我们治不好
It's okay, rodney,
接下来你该说什么
What's the next thing you're supposed to say?
约翰在哪里
Where... where did john go?
他有事得离开几分钟
He just had to go away for a few minutes.
他会马上回来的
He'll be back--
约翰
John!
罗德尼   罗德尼  我是你的好朋友
Rodney... rodney, I'm your friend,
我在这陪你
I'm right here.
约翰  你在哪
Where are you, john?
约翰!
John!
你们怎么不早告诉我  我哥哥病得这么厉害
Why the hell didn't you tell me my brother was this far gone?
吉妮  这一切发生的太突然了
It's happened pretty fast, jeannie.
不  我...
No, i...
几个星期前我还收到他的信息
I got a message from him just a couple of weeks ago.
他   他看起来还很健康
He... he seemed perfectly fine.
他从来没有这么"客气"过
He'd never been so nice.
在他被感染后不久
That would have been
就这样了
Shortly after he became infected.
我没有及时发现症状
I didn't recognize the symptoms in time.
大夫  这不是你的错
It's not your fault, doc.
米勒夫人  坦白的说
Frankly, mrs. miller, we contacted you
我们一发现病症的严重性
As soon as we became aware
就第一时间联系你了
Of the seriousness of his condition.
事实上  当代达罗斯号将你送到
In fact,  daedalus dropped you off
飞马座第一个星门时
At the first available gate in pegasus
我们还担心
Because we were concerned
你可能会来不及赶到这儿
That you wouldn't make it here in time.
我们认为应该给你机会
We thought you deserved a chance
和你哥哥说再见
To say goodbye.
凯勒医生正在和你哥讲
Dr. keller wanted to take a moment
说你要过来看他
To prepare him for your visit.
好的
Yeah, i, uh...
我也需要几分钟来冷静一下
I think I need a moment myself.
他是怎么得上这病的
How did... how did this happen to him?
在执行上一个任务时
Um, there was a little snafu
发了点小问题
On the last mission.
谢帕德中校
Colonel sheppard,
当你抵达研究营
When you reach the research camp,
务必提醒尼克拉斯博士
Please remind dr. nichols
他现在已经...
That he is now...
超过预定报道时间1小时15分钟了
One hour and 15 minutes overdue for his scheduled check-in.
好的  要帮你扁他一下或什么的
Right, want me to smack him around or anything?
只要提醒一下就好  拜托了
Just the reminder, please.
我们不用担心一下尼克拉斯的小分队么?
Shouldn't we be concerned for dr. nichols' team?
不需要  营地和星门只有半小时的路程
No, the settlement's a half hour away from the gate.
他让他们每6小时和总部联系一次
He's got them checking in every six.
我想尼克拉斯一定是满宇宙的跑累了
I'm sure nichols is just tired of taking the round trip.
不管怎么说  他动下手指给总部报个到又不会死
Still, it wouldn't hurt to bust his chops a bit.
那个尼克拉斯太自以为是了
That nichols is so arrogant.
艾米利亚  我想在他们回来报到前
Amelia, I think I'm going to risk
去下面吃个早餐应该来的及
Heading down to breakfast before they check in.
我的意思是
I just mean that...
他们去营地
It will probably take them some time
要花些时间
To get to the camp,
之后尼克拉斯回来报到
And then more time
应该还会更晚点儿
For nichols to get back to the gate and report.
其实我没必要...
There's really no point in my...
说给你听的
Telling you this.
是不必要  长官
Not really, sir.
好的
Right.
20分钟后回来
Be back in 20 minutes.
外来突发激活
Unscheduled offworld activation!
展开防护盾
Activate the shield.
我收不到虹膜解除码
I'm not receiving an idc.
我是谢帕德
This is sheppard.
请不要降低防护盾
Do not lower the shield.
不然整个发射塔将被洪水淹没
The entire tower will be flooded.
中校  我们会继续打开防护盾
I have no intention of doing that, colonel.
你那现在情况怎样
What's your status?
又冷又湿
It's cold and wet.
星门没入水下
The stargate's underwater.
整个山谷也被淹没了
The entire valley's flooded.
我快冻死了
And it's freezing!
我们急需一艘飞船过来
We need you to send a jumper through
好让我们取暖烘干直到洪水退去
So we can stay warm and dry until the water recedes.
马上就到  中校  坚持住
Will do, colonel, hold on.
已经在坚持了
Holding on.
谢帕德汇报完毕
Sheppard out.
救援1号就位
Rescue one is standing by.
怎么这么久
What's taking so long?
为什么星门会罢工
Why isn't the gate disengaging?
是因为这些水
It's the water.
恒压迫使虫洞保持在活跃的状态
The constant pressure's forcing the wormhole to stay active,
这就是说我们得等到
Which means we're going to have to wait
星门所能持续开启的最大时间限度
The maximum amount of time a stargate can stay open.
即38分钟
38 minutes.
那好  现在还剩32分钟
Well, we're down to 32,
别再说什么"我早就告诉过你了"
And before you say I told you so,
我们别无选择
We had no choice.
我冻得一直发抖
I can't stop shivering.
热量都让你从嘴巴漏走了
You're letting all the hot air out of your mouth.
好了弟兄们
All right, everybody,
我们很快会暖起来的
You'll be warm soon enough.
我不知道  我应该湿得比你厉害
I don't know, I think I got wetter than you did.
那我不确定
I don't know,
去拨号也让我弄潮了
I got a little damp dialing the dhd.
研究营在更远一点的山谷里
The research camp was farther up this valley.
我有点担心尼克拉斯的小分队了
I'm a little concerned for dr. nichols' team.
说的对
Right.
研究营里还有人么
Anyone at the research camp,
我是谢帕德中校
This is colonel sheppard.
请回话
Please respond.
重复  我是谢帕德中校
I repeat, this is colonel sheppard.
请回话
Please respond.
我确定他们都死了
I'm pretty sure they're all dead.
我们怎么会知道  罗德尼
We can't know that, rodney.
那些人在研究全球变暖的影响
Look, the research team was studying the effects of global warming.
他们把营扎在山谷深处的冰川脚下
They set up camp at the foot of a massive glacier up the valley.
你觉得是冰化了么
You think an ice dam broke?
有这可能
It fits.
古人不把星门建在这样的冲积平原
The ancients don't put stargates on a flood plain,
我认为也就不会有潮水涌过来
And I certainly don't think the tide just came in.
难怪水这么刺骨的
It explains why the water's so freezing.
好吧
Aw, okay...
我浑身热乎乎的  怎么还是发抖
Okay, so now I'm hot, and I'm still shivering.
在我们出来前  你发烧了么
Were you running a fever before we left?
我不知道  也许吧
I don't know, maybe.
我总是有点什么小毛病
I'm always running something.
好吧
All right,
这水貌似退了一点
I think the water's receded a little.
难道我们要一整晚困在这儿么
So we're going to be stuck here all night.
会有艘温暖舒适的飞船来接我们的
In the back of a warm, cozy jumper, all right?
你要做的就是再坚持
All you need to do is hold on
我不知道  大概30分钟吧
For, I don't know, 30 minutes or so...
他失去知觉多久了
How long has he been unresponsive?
从他在飞船上睡着开始
Since he fell asleep in the jumper.
大概9个小时
About nine hours.
把他送到医务室
Okay, let's get him to the infirmary.
我要做个全身扫描
I want him under a scanner.
你们几个我也得检查一下
I want to have a look at you guys, too.
我们没事
We're good.
那只是暂时的
By that I mean now.
这次事故还是证明了我的提案
I think you've just made a case for my proposal
每单任务都得有一个轮式机器人给你们开路
To send a malp ahead of every single transit.
这是意外  伍尔希
Stuff happens, woolsey,
这意外  我是指...
And by "stuff," I mean--
我知道你指什么  谢谢
I know what you mean, thank you.
你们怎么没乘自己的飞船回来
Why didn't you return in the jumper I sent you?
我让他们
Well, I ordered the rescue party
继续搜救尼克拉斯的小队
to continue the search of nicolas' team
有可能有生还者
There's a chance they're still alive.
说的对
Of course.
我得去做检查了
I got to go get checked out,
然后  去看看罗德尼
And then, uh, I'm going to check on rodney.
我们的小伙怎么样了
Well, how's our boy?
体温正常  没有过高或过低
No fever, no hypothermia,
扫描结果一切正常
Nothing on the scan at all.
你们怎么样了
How about you guys?
我早说了  我们没事
Like I said, we're good.
可是我们都没有昏迷过去
But we're not the ones who became unconscious.
可能是因为昨晚没睡好吧
Well, I didn't really get much sleep the night before,
加上我没好好吃早餐  所以...
And I did skimp on breakfast, so...
知道吗  伍尔希想在每次传送之前都派小机器人
You know, woolsey wants to send out a malp before every transit now.
这样可会减少其使用寿命啊
Well, that's going to get old fast.
我也是这么想的
That's what I said.
我现在能走了么
Hey, can I go now?
躺在这儿我都犯困了
I feel a little silly lying here.
你的观察期得久一点
I'm keeping you under observation for a little longer.
况且  我都帮你订了晚餐了
Besides, I ordered you dinner.
那你还得看着我吃了
Well, then you can observe me eat,
我饿坏了
Because I'm famished.
说真的  他好多了
It's official. he's better.
再见
See you guys.
我把他们带进来好么
Do you want me to send them in?
好的
Okay.
罗德尼准备好见你们了
Rodney's all ready for you.
我该说什么好
What am I supposed to say?
说什么都不要紧了
Doesn't matter.
米尔德斯?
Meredith?
是我  吉妮  米尔  我...
It's me. it's jeannie, mere. I'm--
你是我妹妹
You're my sister.
是的
Yes.
米尔德斯是我...真名
Meredith's my... real name.
嗯  是你的名字
It's your first name, that's right,
可你一直都不喜欢它
But you never liked it.
是不喜欢
No.
是女孩子的名字
No, it's... a girl's name.
有的时候是的
Sometimes, yes,
后来你就改成罗德尼了
But you go by rodney.
罗德尼·麦凯
Rodney mckay,
Mr. rodney mckay.
罗德尼·麦凯  罗德尼·麦凯
Rodney mckay, rodney mckay...
你是因为我哭的
You're crying because of me.
我哭是因为我非常想你
No, I'm crying because I've missed you very much.
因为你是我妹妹
'cause you're my sister.
是的
That's right.
我...
I'm...
生病了
Sick.
我知道
I know.
所以我来了
I'm here now.
我
I...
宝贝  我出去一下好吗
Sweetie, I just need to go outside for one second, okay?
马上回来
I will be right back,
我保证
I promise.
我知道
I know.
给我点时间
I just need a second.
我不想让他看到这样子
I just don't want him to see.
你的心情  我感同身受
I know how you feel.
因为我也一样
I felt the same way.
我会回去的  我会的
I'll go back in, I will.
他需要我  我要跟他道别
He needs me, and I want to be able to say goodbye,
但好像...
But it's like...
他已经弃我而去了
It's like he's already gone.
我知道
I know.
我有个法子
There's a way.
什么  什么办法
What? how?
有个地方  我曾经去过
There's a place. I've been there before.
他能在那里恢复记忆  这样你就能跟他道别
He'll be himself again, and you can say goodbye.
我不太明白
I don't understand,
那你怎么还不带他去
Then why haven't you already taken him?
因为这太危险了
Because it's dangerous,
如果你希望的话  我乐意冒这个险
But I'm willing to risk it if you are.
准备好了么
All set?
别忘了提醒我投诉出这馊主意的人
Remind me to register a complaint with whose ever idea this was.
这可是你的事儿
It was yours, actually.
投诉已经立案了
Well, complaint duly registered.
让你这突如袭来的不测
It was a good idea to keep a record
永载史册  真是个好主意啊
Of what's happening to you and how fast,
不过如果你不愿这样--
But if you'd rather not--
没事儿  这样很好
No, it's fine. it's fine.
记下我的名字呢  对吧
store My name, right?
对
Right.
我还能记得一些事情
Hey, I remembered something. yay!
我是罗德尼·麦凯博士
My name is dr. rodney mckay.
亚特兰蒂斯科学什么部门的头儿
I'm head of the department of science something in atlantis
在...
In the,
老天啊...
Oh, for god's sake...
在飞马座星系...
In the pegasus galaxy.
很好  继续说下去
Okay, not bad, keep going.
珍妮弗  有些...
Jennifer, there's...
有些东西我想  呃...
There's something I wanted to, um...
在我记得  还能记得的时候
You know, while I remember, while I still can,
我想说...
Something I wanted to say...
继续
Go ahead.
吉妮
Jeannie, uh...
真没想到这么晚还会有人来
I wasn't expecting anyone this late.
是啊  我是那种
Yeah, I'm kind of one of those people
对一切必要信息都不肯放过的人
Who needs all the information they can get.
这是他最近一次的头部扫描
This is his most recent scan.
这些看上去像肿瘤的暗色区域
This dark area that looks like a tumor
实际上是一些寄生物
Is actually a parasitic organism.
它的须蔓已经蔓延
Its tendrils spread
利用手术抽离根本无望
Far beyond any hope of surgical extraction,
而且任何疗法对其也毫无效果
And it's not responding to treatment.
即使是抑制状态也很难减缓其蔓延速度
Even stasis barely slowed its progression.
还有很多的混合药物...
There are still a number of drug combinations that--
他是在上次任务中被感染的?
He was infected somehow on his last mission?
有可能
Well, maybe,
但也说不定
But not necessarily.
当时这生物还太小无法在图像上显现
It was too small to show up on a scan at the time,
但在飞马座星系
But in the pegasus galaxy,
这种情况在年长的人中很常见
The condition is fairly common among the very old.
好吧  那为什么是他?
Right, so why him?
很有可能我们都接触过它  但是机体排斥掉了
It's possible we're all exposed to it,and fight it off.
罗德尼在m44 5y9执行任务时
Rodney was already suffering from a viral infection
就已经被毒菌感染了
when he went on the mission at m44 5y9,
之后又长时间浸泡在冰水中--
And then all that time in freezing water--
因此他的抵抗力很差
So his resistance was low.
这种寄生虫并不像是杀死细胞以供其休眠
The parasite doesn't so much as kill cells as render them dormant
其原因我依然没有完全弄明白
For reasons I still don't completely understand,
但最终结果会导致大脑功能不断衰退
But the net result is ever-diminishing brain function.
随着它不断蔓延
As it spreads,
他将失去行动控制能力
He'll lose motor control,
器官功能紊乱--
Regulation of organ function--
若楠的人管这种病叫"老年痴呆"
Ronon's people call the disease "second childhood."
你跟若楠谈过?
You talked to ronon.
是的
Yes.
好吧  我知道他会告诉你些什么
Okay, I know what he's told you.
他说罗德尼快死了  你对此无能为力
That he's dying, and there's nothing you can do.
不  他是要死了  但我将尽我所能帮他
No, he's dying, and I'm doing everything I can.
那我问你...
I have to ask you...
你为什么说你没有及时确诊
Why did you tell me you didn't recognize the symptoms in time?
他执行任务回来以后
Because he was already showing the symptoms
就已经表现出症状
When he came back from the mission, and...
但我都没有见到
I didn't see it.
感觉怎么样
So?
乖乖听医生的安排
Just what the doctor ordered.
你可真幽默
Funny.
来点什锦水果么?
You want my fruit cup?
不  不  不
No, no, no.
口是心非啊
I think you do.
吃病人的东西
Eating from the patient's tray
会引起别人不满的
Is kind of frowned upon.
珍妮弗  我们这是在约会
Jennifer, we practically dated.
你就请我喝了东西  这可跟约会差远了
You bought me one drink. that's hardly dating.
好吧  那如果我现在请你跟我共进晚餐呢
Right, so now I'm asking you to have dinner with me.
我的意思是  比如这个
I mean, such as it is.
我的确挺喜欢什锦水果
I do love the fruit cup.
这可不是我想的那种晚餐  不过...
Not that this is exactly the dinner I had in mind, but...
你在邀请我?
Is that an invitation?
你得先答应
Only if you promise to accept.
如果不是因为被新的罗德尼·麦凯所打动
If I wasn't so taken by the new rodney mckay,
我就能在这些寄生物还小的时候做手术了
The parasite might've been small enough for me to operate
也就不会严重到这个地步了
Without causing significant brain trauma.
到他出现失忆的时候已经太迟了
By the time he started to forget, it was too late.
不过我还没放弃寻找治疗方法
I haven't given up on trying to find a treatment--
若楠告诉我一个地方  能让他在死前暂时清醒的
Ronon told me about this place that could give mere one more day as himself again before he dies.
吉妮  你不能相信...
Jeannie, you can't possibly believe--
你也不想让他去那里?
And that you're the one who won't let him go.
在一个被称为塔勒斯的星球上
It's on a planet called talus.
那是一个先人的原始星球
It's one of the original worlds of the ancestors.
大概需要五到六个小时就能到那里通过星门
It took us about five or six hours to get there From the gate
我那时还只是个孩子
but I was just a kid,
我祖父带我走过大半的路程
And my grandfather had to be carried most of the way.
现在只要花一半的时间就能到那里
We could do it in about half that time.
唯一的问题就是
There's a small problem with that plan.
复制人战争的时候  幽灵族在那里有个大型的前哨基地
The wraith established a major outpost there,during the replicator war.
现在还在
It's still there.
那可挡不住我们去想去的地方
Yeah, well, that's never stopped us from going anywhere we needed to go before.
事实上  并不是仅此而已
Well, it's not just that.
你在怀疑他的真实性
You don't believe it's real.
我可没这么说--
I'm not saying--
我很怀疑
I am, actually.
我去过那里
I was there.
但你当时只有六岁
Yes, but you were six years old.
若楠  想想你告诉我们的
Ronon, listen to what you've told us--
一个魔幻的圣地
A magical shrine,
在一个瀑布后面的山洞里
Inside a cave, behind a waterfall--
我有说过是魔幻的么?
Did I say it was magic?
是没有  但你说那些跟麦凯有相同症状的人
No, but you did say that people afflicted with mckay's condition
突然恢复记忆
Suddenly revert to their former selves for...
很多有这症状的我的族人都知道塔勒斯圣地
The shrine of talus is also known among my people for victims of the second childhood.
去那的人都有一天时间恢复正常
It offers the gift of one last day,
然后迅速死亡
And a quick death.
那也不能说明它的确存在
That doesn't necessarily make it real.
我再次告诉你们
I'm telling you that in a matter of seconds
我见证了我的祖父  从个不知道自己名字的人
I saw my grandfather go from someone who couldn't speak his own name,
变成了个教我追踪打猎的人
To the man that taught me how to track and hunt.
你六岁的时候就学习打猎?
You learned to hunt when you were six years old?
突然有一天
For one day,
他抱着他的妻子
He got to hold his wife in his arms,
然后与他爱的人共进一餐
And share a meal with the people that he loved,
接着光荣地死去了
And then he died with honor.
你可以认为我当时太小记不住
You can say I was too young to remember,
但我知道我看到了什么
But I know what I saw,
并且现在我们可以为麦凯做同样的事
And we can do the same thing for mckay.
你要是觉得这不值得
If you think that's not worth it,
你就错了
You're wrong.
我从没对外人提过这件事情
I've never told anyone this,outside of...
我父亲得了老年痴呆
My father had a disease called alzheimer's.
这跟麦凯博士的病症很像
It's similar in many respects to the condition that dr. mckay is suffering from.
我的意思是...
My point is,
跟你刚才说的一致
I had a similar moment with him to the one you just described.
几个月过去了  他已经认不出我是谁了
He hadn't recognized me, literally, for months,
直到有一天  很突然的
Then one day, out of the blue,
他突然对一切重新恢复记忆
He had a moment of absolute clarity.
他对我说"理查,你在这里干嘛呢?"
He said "richard, what are you doing here?"
然后我对他说"爸,我...我来看你"
And I said, "dad, i, uh,I'm here to see you,"
然后他说...
And he said...
他说"那岂不是好极了?"
He said, "isn't that wonderful,"
然后他又再一次陷入以往的状态
And then he was gone again.
你难道记不起一点类似的...
Now, couldn't you be remembering a similar--
那可不一样
It's not the same.
若楠
Ronon, look--
我欠他的!
I owe him this!
我自己带他去
I'll take it myself.
我跟你一块
I'll go with him.
等等  等等
Hold on, hold on.
都知道我们只有两艘母船
We know for a fact there are two hive ships
而地面上有大概10,000幽灵族
And 10,000 wraith on the ground.
要是不得不这样做的话  好吧
If we're even going to consider this, all right,
我们得先制定个计划
We have to make a plan.
好吧  制定你的计划
Fine, make your plan.
抱歉各位  没有我的允许他哪儿也不能去
I'm sorry, but he's not going anywhere without my permission,
而等我们和罗德尼谈过以后再做决定
And you won't get that until we talk to rodney.
还好吧  罗德尼
Hey, rodney...
有人来看你了
You got some visitors.
约翰来了
John's here.
还有泰勒跟若楠
So are teyla and ronon.
全队都到了
The whole team.
若楠·德克斯
Ronon dex.
没错  伙计
That's right, buddy.
我想带你去个地方
I want to take you to a place,
在那儿你能短时间恢复记忆
A place that's going to give you a chance to be yourself again for a little while.
回到你生病之前那样
As you were before you became ill.
之前?
Before...
嘿  老兄
Hey, pal.
约翰
Hey, j-john.
事实上  我们不...知道你身上将发生什么事
Truth is, we don't... know exactly what's going to happen to you,
但如果你愿意的话我们会全力帮助你
But we're willing to try, if you are.
没问题
Okay.
你同意了
那  安顿好他  然后
Okay, well, that settles it, then.
不行  还不行
No, it doesn't.
罗德尼  他们没告诉你全部细节
Rodney, they haven't told you everything.
他没必要知道
He doesn't need to know.
他们想要带你去的那个行星
The planet they want to take you to
是个幽灵族的前哨基地
Is a wraith outpost.
你还记得什么是幽灵族么
You remember who the wraith are?
你要是去的话  会非常非常危险
It means going will be very,very dangerous,
不仅是对你而言  还有你的朋友
Not just for you, but for your friends.
我们乐意冒这个险
We're willing to take that risk.
为了什么去冒这个险
A risk for which, and I'm sorry--
就算有用  这点我还是怀疑...
even if it works,Which I very much doubt--
总有一天你会好起来的
You might revert to your former self for one day.
原谅我这种语气  听起来很不吉利
Now, forgive me if that sounds more like torture than a blessing.
我们一直在想尽办法处理这个问题
We're still coming up with new ideas on how to treat this thing,
但是如果你这坚持这么做
But if you do this,
坚持离开亚特兰蒂斯
if you leave atlantis...
亚特兰蒂斯...
Atlantis...
这一切就完了
It's over.
我就帮不上你了
I can't help you.
大夫
Doctor...
他根本就不明白
He doesn't understand.
你错了  他明白
No, he doesn't,
他去留的决定权在我这儿
Which means the decision on whether or not to let him go is mine,
我绝不会放弃我的病人
And I haven't given up on trying to cure my patient.
你还是不放弃啊
And you still haven't given up .
不  因为我不认为
No, because I don't think
这些细胞上的损伤是永久性的
The damage to the cells is permanent,
这就意味着
Which means
只要我能成功地移除寄生虫...
If I can to safely remove the parasite--
你已经花了多长时间在这上面
How long have you been at it?
好几周了吧?
Weeks?
可是他还能撑几天
And how many days does he have left?
最多两天不是吗
Two at most?
我知道你尽力了
Look, I know you've done everything you can.
我知道你觉得这是你的责任
I know you feel responsible,
你一直在努力寻找解决的办法  可是...
And you want to keep trying, but...
我是他的近亲
I'm his next of kin.
所以还是按我的决定吧
That makes the decision mine.
我们要带他去
and we're taking him
正在录了
It's recording.
难道你不说"开拍"之类的么
Well, aren't you supposed to say, "action" or something?
不好意思啦
Oh, sorry.
说笑而已
I'm kidding.
我们开始吧
Okay, here we go.
我的名字是罗德尼·麦凯博士
My name is dr. rodney mckay.
在飞马座星系  亚特兰蒂斯里
I am head of the science and research departments
我是负责科学研究部门的
Here in atlantis, in the pegasus galaxy,
在目前的这片地方
In the local cluster,
甚至我们所认识的宇宙
In the universe as we know it.
录制这个日志是为了
The purpose of this log
给我自己  也给凯勒医生
Is to provide a baseline for myself,
提供一份资料
And for dr. keller,
用来关注我的进展  关于我的...
To monitor the progress of my, um...
失忆
Memory loss.
很搞笑  对吧
Ironic, isn't it?
先从复述前面提到的开始
By reciting the aforementioned,
同时再列举一些事情
As well as a list of things
那些我了如指掌的信息
I know like the back of my hand,
那么从圆周率开始吧  精确到小数点后的第12位
Starting with pi, to, say, 12 decimals.
3.1415926535...
罗德尼在船上么
Rodney on board?
是的
Yes.
我们之前达成的协议没有异议吧
Are we clear on the rules of engagement?
我们的行动不会让幽灵人发现的
We'll get in and get out before the wraith even know it.
谢帕德中校
Colonel sheppard,
如果麦凯确实恢复了记忆
If in fact dr. mckay does regain his...
替我跟他道个别
Say goodbye for me.
我以为你不相信
I thought you didn't believe.
那是先决条件?
Is that a prerequisite?
你能来他很高兴
He'll be glad you're here.
好吧  搞定这件事  要么能成  要么就不成
All right, we're either going to get away with this, or we're not.
要是不成  这趟旅程应该会很辛苦
If we don't, the ride's going to wild,
而且速度很快  大家要有所准备
And it's is going to be fast, so I need everyone prepared.
3号飞船
Jumper three,
准备就位
Standing by.
先送辆轮式小机器人吧
Send the malp through.
它们已经帮你们清除了了障碍物
The malp is clear of the gate,
并且向两旁开火
And they're firing on it from both sides
看起来是个深山谷
Of what appears to be a deep valley.
它们正在制造烟雾罩
It's deploying smoke.
使这片地区隐形5秒钟
You should have complete coverage of the area in five seconds.
好的  明天见
Okay, see you tomorrow.
但愿如此
I hope so.
这山谷真骇人啊
That's one hell of a valley.
能赶在他们探测到我们之前就隐形起来么
Do you think they detected us before we were able to cloak?
应该可以  烟雾罩应该起作用了
No, I think the smokescreen worked.
但愿他们认为
Hopefully they think
我们是派了个机器人开路
We just sent a malp through ahead of us
然后他们把它炸掉了就能震慑我们
And changed our mind when they blew it up.
我要扫描一下着陆点了
All right, I'm going to do a sweep of the landing area.
花不了几分钟
Shouldn't take more than a few minutes.
约翰  约翰!
John, john!
约翰!
John!
你就在那  然后他...
You were there, and-and then he--
罗德尼  罗德尼  我在这儿呢  出什么事了
Rodney, rodney, I'm right here. what's wrong?
我醒过来  大家都走了
I woke up, everyone had left!
兄弟  我...
Buddy, i...
抱歉  我以为你睡着了
I'm sorry, I thought you'd fallen asleep.
我...
I was...
我怕极了  我很肯定...
I got so scared, I was sure that...
一到早上我残存的意识一定会消失殆尽的
By the morning what was left of my mind was going to be gone!
我送你回房间好么
I'm going to take you back to your quarters, okay?
约翰  我从没这么害怕过
John... john, I've never been so scared.
我抓不住了
I'm slipping away.
它要溜走了
I'm slipping away,
我不知道怎么办
And I don't know how to stop myself!
看  你还在这里啊
Look, you're still here.
没事的
All right?
你还在这里啊
You're still here.
对啊  我是啊
Yeah. I am.
而我也还在这里啊
And I'm not going anywhere.
如果你想出去逛逛  那就...
You know, you want to hang out, you just...
出去逛逛
Hang out.
我不知道要做什么
I don't know what to do.
我不知道该拿自己怎么办
I don't know what to do with myself.
我...
I'm...
对不起  我不该吵醒你
I'm sorry, I shouldn't have woken you up.
没关系  看外面夜色多美妙
All right, look, it's a nice night out.
我们去码头上喝些啤酒吧
Let's go have some beer on the pier, okay?
我会喝酒?
I drink beer?
非常能喝
A lot.
拿着这个
Take this.
快点呀  兄弟  我们走!
Come on, buddy, let's go.
我不清楚  我能再喝一瓶吗
I don't know, should I have another?
喝了也无妨
What could happen?
我不该那样砸你的门
I shouldn't have banged on your door like that.
感觉好荒唐
I feel ridiculous.
不要这么想
Don't.
我一直在想
I've been trying to remember the name
我侄儿的名字
Of my sister's kid.
贝蒂
Betty.
贝蒂...
Betty...
我敢保证肯定不是这个
Pretty sure that's not it.
It's madison. see?
至少你能想起来什么不是了
At least you remembered what it wasn't.
这只是下下策
Oh, there's an underrated skill.
我只是说  也许没有你想象的那么糟糕啊
I'm just saying you may not be as far gone as you think.
我在掩饰了
I'm hiding it.
真的  我已经忘记了很多东西
Believe me, I've already forgotten more
比大家所能想象的要多得多
Than most people will ever know,
我知道这听起来很...
And I know that sounds...
自大  对吧
Arrogant, is that right?
嗯
Yeah.
是这样
That works.
早上我在帮泽兰卡弄一个装置
This morning I was trying to help zelenka finish a device
那本来是我想出来的
That was apparently my idea.
我没用了
I was useless.
珍妮弗说我还会继续恶化
Jennifer says it's going to get worse now
再一个小时最多
Almost by the hour.
差不多一周以后
In a week or so,
我甚至记不住我自己的名字
I won't even remember my name.
这样吧...
How's about...
我们现在就说再见吧
How about we say goodbye now?
不要
No.
你说不要是什么意思
What do you mean, no?
我是说  我不要说再见
I mean, I'm not saying goodbye.
反正我会说的
Well, I'm saying it anyway.
那我就当没听见
I'm not listening.
可是很快我就会不知道你是谁了啊
Yeah, but pretty soon I won't even know who you are.
那我会提醒你
Then I'll remind you.
可是我不希望你看到我那个样子
But I don't want you to see me like that.
我想让你记住我现在的样子
I want you to remember me as I am,
一个天才  而不是什么...
As your genius friend, not as some --
不可能
Not happening.
拜托了嘛
Please.
你别和我争了  罗德尼
You're stuck with me, rodney.
面对现实吧
Just accept it.
可是...
Yeah, but--
没有可是!
No!
就这样!
That's final.
好吧
Okay.
你真是个好朋友
You're a good friend, arthur.
着陆点没有发现问题
All right, landing area's clear.
我们准备进入了
I'm taking us in.
我们是要去哪
Where are we going?
那儿  看到了吗
Up there, do you see?
瀑布后面  那有个洞
Behind the waterfall, there is a cave,
当我们到了那
And when we get there, you will spend
你就可以和朋友们在一起了
A wonderful day with your friends.
可我很累
I'm tired.
我知道
I know.
我们很快就到了
We'll be there soon.
然后呢  我们怎么办
So... what do we do?
等
We wait.
罗德尼
Rodney...
看这瀑布
Look at the waterfall.
很棒对吧
It's cool, huh?
一点也不
No.
能量读数很弱了
I'm getting very faint energy readings.
哪种的能量读数
What kind of energy readings?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
看看这个
Look at this.
放射物?
Radiation?
我从没见过这种的
Not that I've ever seen.
说不定可以问下罗德尼
Maybe we can ask rodney in a minute.
约翰!
John!
撑着点  兄弟
Just hang in there, buddy.
我要回家!
I want to go home now!
或许他得靠得再近一点这个图
Perhaps he should stand closer to this tablet.
我不知道
I-- I don't know.
这应该是能量读数的来源点了
I think that's the source of these energy readings.
我现在就要回去!
I want to go now!
就再一下下就好
A little bit longer.
我要回去!
Go now!
吉妮?
Jeannie?
我在这  米尔
I'm here, mere.
这很明显嘛
Yeah, obviously.
他回来了
He's back.
谁来告诉我下
Somebody please tell me
见鬼了我们在这里干吗
What the hell we're all doing here?
罗德尼·麦凯
rodney mckay
我是科学和...  和...
i'm head of science and... and ...
研究
research
-没关系的  -很有关系!
- it's ok. - No,it's not!
亚特兰蒂斯
atlantis...
飞马座
Pegasus...
3.14...
It's 3.1...4...
我不知道
I don't know.
我怎么可能不知道
How can I not know that?
要不要先停一会儿
Do you want to stop?
当我一闭上眼
I keep seeing a face.
我的眼前总有张脸在晃动
Every time I close my eyes.
我想那应该是我妈妈
I think it's my mother.
我...  我不...
I don't-- I don't...
我认不出她来了...那是很早以前的事了
R-recognize her... it's so long ago.
她一直在说着什么
She's saying words to me...
可是我不知道她在说什么
I don't know them.
那你们想从这个鬼地方开始?
Well, you can start with, what is this place?
这里是塔勒斯的圣地
It's the shrine of talus.
那对我来说什么都不是
That means nothing to me.
这是先人的星球
It's a planet of the ancestors.
所以我们带你来了这里
We brought you here.
谢谢啊  全知先生
Thank you, mr. information.
若楠什么时候学会解释了
Since when did he become ronon the explainer,
而且我怎么不在医务室里
And why am I not in the infirmary, huh?
我好转了?
What am i, better?
我是好多了
I am better!
并没有的
No, you're not.
有啊  我感觉到了  真是太神奇了
I am. I can feel it. this is amazing!
我们把你带到这儿来
Mere, we brought you here
是为了我们能有个机会跟你说再见
So we could have a chance to say goodbye to each other,
你这样的状态也就差不多持续1天
But you're only going to feel like this for about a day.
因为规律就是这样
That's just how it works.
什么什么什么?!
Whoa, whoa, whoa. what?
你记得吗
What do you remember?
我记得你不让我说再见的
I remember you not wanting me to say goodbye then.
可是现在唱的又是哪一出
Why now all of a sudden?
还有  什么只有一天
Look, and why one day?
那又是什么
What's with that?
这是圣地的魔力
It is a gift of the shrine,
我们冒着危险把你带到这儿来
And from all of us who risked great danger to bring you here,
也给你最后一个机会  和你爱的人们在一起
One last chance to be with those you love.
然后呢
And then what?
我就要死了吗
I die?
光荣地
With honor.
带着尊严
And dignity.
去他的  那我就一直呆在这
Screw that, I'll just stay here.
没有用的
Doesn't work that way.
为什么
Why not?
这个星球是幽灵人控制的
One, this is a wraith-controlled planet.
而且我们也探测到
And we're detecting
电离辐射
Ionizing radiation.
实际上我们也不应该站得这么近...
In fact, we shouldn't be standing this close to the--
你们在开什么玩笑
You've got to be kidding me.
你怎么能让他们这么对我
How could you let them do this to me?
不能怪她
Don't blame her.
她也不想这么做的
She didn't even want to do this.
那是谁出的这馊主意的
Then whose brilliant idea was it?
我
Mine.
我们都认为这是件好事
We all thought it was a good thing--
这怎么可能是件好事
How could this possibly be a good thing?
我都放下面子了
Look, I'd got past the humiliation,
跟你们一一道别
I've said my goodbyes.
我很遗憾你发生了这样的事
Meredith, I'm sorry this happened to you,
可是对于这个机会我不后悔
But I'm not sorry that I got this chance.
拜托啊  就...
Please, just...
试着当成是一次机会而不是...
Try to see this as an opportunity and not--
折磨?
Not torture?
对不起  我...
Look, I'm sorry, I just...
我以为我慢慢好转了
I thought I was going to be okay,
可是你们却说...
And then now you tell me...
那有没有计划点什么乐子
Did you have some kind of itinerary planned?
事实上
Well, actually,
我们先去饱餐一顿
We're going to have a big feast first.
最后的晚餐?
Last supper, huh?
当然  配合你的弥赛亚情结
Well, suits your messiah complex.
那倒是
True.
别生我的气啊
Please don't be mad at me.
如果非得要我选
I guess if I had to choose
我的最后一天跟谁过的话...
The people I would spend my last day with, then...
怎么了
What is it?
老实说  我真没期望能有效果
Honestly, I didn't expect it to work.
我希望什么事都不会发生  也确实没发生
I expected nothing would happen, and that would be that.
所以  我们为什么要这么做
So why did it?
跟我一样
You don't believe in magic shrines
你也不相信这圣地有奇迹
Any more than I do.
给他看下读数
Show him the readings.
嗯...
Hmm.
我就是这么说的
That's what I said.
你说"嗯"?
You said "hmm"?
我是说我也觉得很诡异
I just meant that I thought it was weird, too.
你怎么看  某种反物质?
So what do you think, antimatter?
或者是某种超重元素
Or a superheavy element
古人曾用来当作能量源的
The ancients used to use as an energy source.
我从来没见过这个
I've never seen it before--
或者制造出来给这个地方供给能源的
Or created to power whatever this place used to be.
这谁知道呢  都几千年了吧
Who could tell what that is? must be thousands of years--
看这脉冲
whoa, see that spike?
快点来  这是给你办的派对
Come on, this is your party.
玩得开心点
Let's have some fun.
对我来说  这个才是开心的
For me, this is fun.
给我留点火腿
Just... save me some ham.
看  又一次
Whoa, there it goes again.
看起来就像间歇的伽马射线
It's like some kind of intermittent gamma that's--
跟我来
Come with me.
干吗  为什么
What? why?
我得确认一些事情
Because I need to find out something.
我们去哪
Where are we going?
幸运的话就一直走回亚特兰蒂斯
Hopefully all the way back to atlantis.
对不起
Sorry...
你为什么要这么做
Why did you do that?
想看看那些寄生虫
To determine whether the parasite
当我们把他带离放射源的话
Would expand rapidly back into his brain
会不会又加速扩张到他的大脑里
When we took him from the radiation source,
而且我认为就是这样子
And I think it did.
他的症状之所以
The reason why his symptoms disappeared
一到这儿来就消失
When we came here
是因为它收缩了以便自我保护
Was because it contracted to protect itself.
好吧  那这说明什么
All right, well, what does that mean for us?
离开这个地方会置他于死地
That leaving this chamber will probably kill him.
我们不能把他带回亚特兰蒂斯
We can't take him back to atlantis.
所以...
So...
我们得想个法子
We're going to have to find a way
让我能在这里给他动手术
A way for me to operate on him right here.
我以为你已经试过反射疗法了
i thought you already tried radiation
我是试过了  可是我没碰到过这种类型的
i did,but we never came across this kind before
寄生虫对辐射有反应  所以这里才会起作用
the parasite is radio-sensetive to it that's why the shrine works
这里的辐射让它们感觉到不舒服
it feels fine for one day until radiation start to making it feel sick
-可是人一离开  -它们就又迅速进入大脑
-and then you leave -the parasite began to back in your brain
今天又要开始忙活了  我晓得啦
the day is over i get it
那这地方够操作吗
so here is it small enough to operate?
我是这么设想的
Well, I'm guessing here,
这是唯一一点我能想到的
But it's the only thing I can think of
能对他的好转做出解释
That would explain his sudden remission,
但是没有直接看到我也不能很确定
But I'm not going to know for certain until I get in there.
可是用战地装备能搞定这个么
How are you going to manage that with a field kit?
不用这些
I don't.
我们得去亚特兰蒂斯搬器材过来
We would have to bring equipment back from atlantis.
这就是问题所在
Well, that's a problem.
要是我们呼叫亚特兰蒂斯
What if we radio atlantis,
让他们送个小飞船过来
Ask them to send a jumper through
带上我需要的东西呢?
With what I need?
不  我们不能这么做
No, we can't.
我需要那些设备  约翰
I need that equipment, john.
听着  幽灵人
Well, the wraith
不可能再上当一次的
Are never going to fall for the same trick twice.
就算如果他们没有截获我们的无线电信号
Even if somehow they don't pick up on our radio signal,
即使第2艘飞船成功地到达了这里
And even if the second jumper makes it through the gauntlet,
他们就会知道我们在这里
They'll know we're here.
我们就在也回不去亚特兰蒂斯了
We'll never make it back to atlantis.
如果我们不试试  他就会死的
If we don't try, he's dead.
你需要什么
What do you need?
手术用?  我已经告诉过你了
To operate? I already told you.
不是  我指最简装备  得包括什么
No, bare minimum, what do you need?
反正不止我的医药箱里那些东西
more than i have in my medical kit.
得要一个扫描仪
I mean, I need a scanner
来确定寄生虫的位置
To find out the location of the parasite,
还得有些适当的工具
I need the proper tools
把他的脑壳给割开
To cut his skull open--
好吧
All right.
我有主意了
I've got an idea.
尽可能的让他远离这东西
Keep him as far away from this thing as he can stand.
我们20分钟之内就回来
We'll be back in 20 minutes.
你不会想让我用这些吧
You can't expect me to operate with those.
我见过手术钻的
Well, I've seen surgical drills.
没有什么不同
They're not that much different.
好吧  那就算我们动了刀子
F-fine, assuming we can open him up,
我们还是没有办法确认
I still have no way of knowing
寄生虫是缩到哪个角落的
Where the parasite has contracted to.
我们可以用这个
We can use this.
生命迹象探测器?
A lifesigns detector?
有何不可
Yeah. why not?
它不是用来探测
Well, it's just not designed to do
我想要探测的东西
What I need it to do
不是同一个尺度
On the correct scale.
那我们可以让吉妮来调整
Oh, we'll have jeannie modify it.
你不了解的
No. you don't understand.
那个放射物
The radiation
就在我们说话的当下  正在损害他的免疫系统
Is compromising his immune system as we speak,
如果我们没害死他
Which means if I don't kill him,
在潮湿的洞穴里动手术
The infection he's bound to get
有可能造成的感染
By being operated on in a damp cave
同样也会置他于死地
Almost certainly will!
可如果我们不采取点什么措施的话
Look, if we don't do something,
他必死无疑
He's dead.
你说过的
You said it.
绝对不要
Absolutely not!
我们是想救你
We're talking about saving your life.
我的脑袋
Look, my brain
可不是你家后院
Is not some new deck
的什么新墙壁
Off the back of your house.
又不是我来动手术的
I'm not the one doing the surgery.
就算给我的临终赠言
Yes, and as my parting advice,
你就应该阻止他们
You need to stop letting these guys talk you
让你做这么愚蠢的事情
Into doing stupid things.
我可以的
I can do it.
真的吗
Really?
我也确定我能调节这个探测器
And I'm fairly sure I can modify the lifesigns detector.
是啊  在我的帮助下
Yeah, with my help...
那就帮忙吧
So help.
这不是什么脑颅手术
This isn't one of those pbs brain surgeries
要大开我的脑壳吧
Where my skull is wide open,
而且我们还在讨论...
And we're having a conversation...
我有足够的麻醉药
I have enough anesthetic to put you out.
你不会有什么感觉的
You're not going to feel a thing.
这值得商榷
Yeah, it's probably a hammer.
时间就是生命  罗德尼
Time is of the essence, rodney.
做个决定吧
You need to make a decision.
来吧  米尔
Please, mere.
我们试一试吧
Let us try.
看来就我是反对派
Look, obviously I'd get around to consenting.
一口气丢给我这么多可怕的事情
It's just-- you've thrown an awful lot at me all at once.
这就是生活
That's life.
好吧  我要吃点火腿
All right, well, let me have a little ham.
术前禁食
No. no food before surgery.
拜拜  吉妮
Bye, jeannie.
我有时太刻薄了  抱歉
Sorry I'm mean sometimes.
拜拜  泰勒
Bye. bye, teyla.
拜拜  若楠·德克斯
Bye, ronon dex.
拜拜  约翰
Bye, john.
拜拜
Bye.
我准备在这儿
I'm going to have to cut here...
这儿
Here...
还有这
And here,
从这些点钻进去
And drill those points
切除这一块
To resect the area.
好的
Okay.
我不准备穿透硬脑膜层
I don't want to penetrate the dura layers
除非必须
Until we get to that stage,
所以你尽量稳住他吧
So hold him as still as you can.
开始吧
Go.
我花太多时间来设置探测器了
I took too long reconfiguring the lifesigns detector.
该死  我钻太深了
Dammit, I went too far.
稳住他
Hold him steady.
我在努力了
I'm trying.
是寄生虫
It's the parasite...
在动了
It's moving.
也许它知道我们在找它
Well, maybe it knows we're going after it.
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
它应该是本能地想要
I think it instinctually wants
逃开放射源
To get away from the radiation source,
我们这样只是给它提供了出口
And we've just shown it the way out.
若楠  枪借我们10秒钟
Ronon, we're going to need that gun of yours in about 10 seconds.
你用脚踩就好了嘛
You could have stepped on it.
她说用枪的
She told me to shoot it.
干净了
It's clear.
干的不错
You did a good job.
你也是
You too.
我们带他回家吧
Let's get him home.
你去睡会儿觉吧
Why don't you go get some sleep?
我整晚都在这里
I'm going to be here all night.
没事
It's okay.
我想看着他醒来
I'd like to be here when he wakes up.
那应该还要一段时间
Well, it could be a while.
我们的罗德尼是爱睡觉的呀
He does love to sleep, our rodney.
你真该看看他小时候
You should've seen him when he was a teenager.
这么吵谁能睡得着啊
Who can sleep with all the talking?
嗨
Hi.
你的...  记忆都还在吗
You still, uh, all there?
还可以装下很多呢
Well, there was so much to spare.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不用客气
You're welcome.
那真吓人
That was scary.
我也是
For me too.
饿吗
Are you hungry?
饿极了
Peckish.
我去帮你弄点吃的
I'll go order you something.
珍妮弗  有些事我想告诉你
Jennifer, there's something I wanted to...
趁着我还记得  趁着我还能说
While I remember, while I still can,
有些事我想告诉你
There's something I wanted to say before, uh...
说吧
Go ahead.
我...
I, uh...
我爱你
I love you.
有一段时间了
Loved you for some time now.
好吧  我在哪...
Okay, where was i...